wow
um
[Music]
hello everybody
welcome to episode 56 of ask average
today is a live video chat show as you
know and i am going to share the link
for joining the video chat
very shortly so first of all i would
like to say
okay first of all let's see who all is
there i can see abhishek nita harshit
sushant vivek
sushrut sampriti satyam
[Music]
lots of other people nice to see you all
very nice to see you all
so i am sharing the video chat link
right now and uh
i have a request for those of you who
have joined before
so
i would like to bring in new people
today i mean some people have joined the
video chat several times in the past
even though i requested them not to uh i
realized later that some people managed
to sneak in multiple times
so the request to all of you is that
please if you already have joined the
video chat in the past in past episodes
then don't
join today so that new people get the
opportunity to join the video chat right
so it's a
request to all of you
please don't do that
i am sharing the video chat link right
now
here it is one second let me pin it so
that you can all see it
hopefully you should be able to see the
video chat link now so you can start
joining it
and the second rule is that
uh
like i've said before one question per
person that's it
i want everybody to get the opportunity
to ask questions if you if people are
asked multiple questions then it's going
to be i want to treat everybody equally
so please just uh
ensure that you ask only one question
per person do not request me to take
multiple questions
and so on so forth
right so shall we begin the q and a
session
i can see lots of people have joined
that is wonderful
so
let us begin with uh
okay hang on
let me first put on my headphones today
i have headphones all right let's go
so whom do i ask let's bring in shibby
hello sheepy how are you doing
yes sir i'm fine fine i'm shibi i'm from
tamil nadu
and i'll go with my question first okay
sir uh i once explained your ideas on
gandhi and how he's our british so here
goes my question i saw you representing
your views on the youtube channel
argumentative indians uh based on was
india's partition inevitable and the
theory wasn't accepted very much among
other co-founders like
and so on so forth so question number
one how prevalent is this theory and
what are the major river tills and this
is another doubt i have about indian
languages so that's it
what's which theory are you referring to
uh no i'm saying that why isn't uh
is gandhi a british huge uh is it widely
expected uh i mean widely accepted or
what are the major revertals
okay great right uh it is not widely
accepted at all that he uh worked on
behalf of the british order that he that
he was a british stooge
uh the prevalent view about mr mohandas
gandhi is that he was a great freedom
fighter a great humanist he was a great
humanitarian he was somebody who
believed in non-violence he was somebody
who believed in world peace and so on
and so forth and
he worked for the benefit and the
upliftment of all humanity so that is
the way the world views mr gandhi he is
viewed as a great saint is somebody who
is even higher than the nobel prize
nobel peace prize and so on so that is
the
mainstream accepted view
worldwide of mr gandhi of course now
people have begun
examining his uh
his life especially his own writings
and if you examine his own writings a
completely different image of mr gandhi
comes to light the writings are
available in the public domain available
for free
anybody can go and read them but the
problem is people you know don't read so
that's the problem now some people have
begun to read that and
it has been realized that first of all
mr gandhi had extremely uh negative
views about
african origin people so he spent a
significant period of his life in south
africa
and the things he wrote about the native
africans were
well
well the only term you can use for that
is racist
mr gandhi wrote that he regarded the
europeans as the pre-dominating race in
the world he saw indians as inferior to
the british to the white european people
and he saw the africans as the lowest of
of all that's what he wrote now see the
fact is that people's opinions change
over time people's views evolve over
time
but when somebody
changes their opinion and realizes that
what they had said in the past was
completely wrong it was hurtful racist
and so on then they would up they would
issue an apology especially if they have
expressed such views in writing
because that is what you have written
down in writing is there forever and
therefore it is incumbent it behaves you
to issue a clarification and an apology
for having expressed such views in the
past that is what any mature human being
would do mr gandhi never apologized he
never retracted retracted those
statements
that is something that people don't
realize people say here people change
people evolve maybe he believed that
when he was younger later he may have
changed his opinion but he never
expressed a change in opinion even
though he wrote those things in the past
that's number one
and yeah so if you examine his writings
and all he has clearly said that he has
dedicated his life to the service of the
british crowd if you look at his actions
not his words then you see that all his
actions were beneficial to the british
and eventually to the partition and so
on and so forth right so if you examine
actions and even his writings then a
totally different view of mr gandhi
emerges now obviously
people
especially
mainstream historians established
historians are extremely unwilling to
accept such a
revised a view of mr gandhi because they
have been expressing a certain viewpoint
and people
are pretty entrenched in their opinions
and in their thoughts and in their stand
so like uh so i was on that channel
what's it called argumentative indians
or something
and the entire panel was against me
especially the pakistanis and all it is
very strange that even the pakistanis
are pretty uh they they have a very good
opinion of mr gandhi which tells you a
lot about mystic
okay i apologize but i have to allow
only one question per person
all right
thank you so much thank you so much very
good question nice meeting you right
bye-bye
all right let's take in somebody else
whom shall we bring in somebody who has
not been in here before
if any of you who are in here right now
have been on this channel before then i
would request you
to kindly
leave the chat
right
okay uh because i think i think people
have realized that i am not good at
remembering faces i meet so many people
i and interact with so many people that
i kind of
tend to forget the people's faces once
i'm
done interacting with them so please
don't take advantage of that please
okay let's bring in somebody let's bring
in mr um
hello
hello hello
how are you doing
just one minute
what's your question sir where are you
from
i think there's some sort of a
lag unfortunately
i'm gonna wait for a second
hello
yes uh what's uh where are you from
what's your question
yeah uh
i am unable to hear you i'm very sorry
i'm very sorry
it's a i'm you're not audible
unfortunately
uh please make it fast because everybody
is waiting you know
we have to respect the audience's time
i'm extremely sorry just one minute
okay you can come in later perhaps okay
let's bring in somebody else
let's bring in
mr vinumbra
good evening sir where are you from
hello
am sir
audible to you
yes you are
uh hi sir uh so i am from jabalpur
madhya pradesh
all right nice to meet you yeah uh uh
likewise sir sir i'll just uh speak in
uh hindi okay
it's much better and more elaborative
than the western music
so i just want your opinion
in that yeah very good question
hindustani classical music indian
classical music see mera background
especially actually classical music it's
been a hobby of mine for the past 24
years it's i have been interested in
music it's some it's something i i used
to play the guitar and all in the past i
have no longer i
i no longer at the time and all but i
used to play indian rags and all that on
the guitar so i have some kind of a
theoretical and conceptual understanding
of what uh hindustani classical music is
so hindustani classical music
that's the question right where did it
originate from where did it come from so
unfortunately nobody has done this
historical historical research it is the
largest corpus of uh
of
his of our musical scales and and more
than that in the entire world it's an
extremely complex and vast system
musical system it's it's
i mean
to develop something as vast as that it
would take i think millennia thousands
of years for instance you have certain
ragas which are known to have changed
over the centuries a raga is essential
essentially a scale of notes
in case you don't know that we have
seven notes in in music
c d e f g a b c and so on and you have a
notes in between that c minor g g sharp
and so on so out of all these notes you
can create rules and patterns and those
are called scales
so that is what western music is all
about it's all about scales so in the
ragas also you have scales but in ragas
in ascending and descending you can have
different scales and then you have a
sonar note a consonant node you have
drone drone notes and all so that
imposes a great deal of restriction but
and a great deal of discipline but gives
you complete total freedom within that
and it allows musicians to create
moods each raga has a certain mood each
raga expresses a certain time or a
season of the year a time of the day
there are morning ragas evening ragas
dusk dawn night afternoon and so on
there are monsoon ragas and all
and if you listen to this it actually
evokes the feeling of that season or
that that time of the day it every raga
has a certain personality a certain mood
and so on it's an extremely complex and
and
profound system of music that the west
has never been able to ever achieve that
kind of uh profundity and that level of
sophistication right
so it's clear that this system is
extraordinary old extraordinarily old it
must have been there for thousands of
years unfortunately there is i mean we
have all these history departments in
india what do they what research do they
do has any any historian in this country
taken up the study and the and the
research of indian classical music which
is a fascinating field it is the most
advanced and sophisticated system of
music in the entire world it is it is
orders of magnitudes higher than western
classical music and unfortunately nobody
has done that so all i can say is that
it is clearly several thousand years old
it must have begun with the dawn of
indian civilization which is at least 10
000 years old and over time it must have
evolved it is a system that is
it is a continuous system an unbroken
system musicians generation after
generation have uh
added to what their predecessors have
done so it's a fascinating fascinating
system unfortunately it's dying out
today i mean everybody is going to the
bollywood style music western music
and the instruments are becoming
obsolete the musicians no longer have
the incentive to spend their entire life
learning this when you can make quick
money and have a better life you know
doing bollywood music and so on it's
it's uh it's it's it's very sad this is
happening i wish the government would do
something to preserve indian classical
music and actually even take it further
because with modern technology with
modern instrumentation and all you can
actually take it to the next level you
know but unfortunately it's not being
done so all i can say unfortunately is
that i don't know when it started it's
clearly many thousand years old it's the
oldest system of music in the world
because even the western uh music
follows the same set of seven notes and
all that the chinese system of music is
a pentatonic system it has only five
notes
but we have a hexagonic system we even
have uh more complex uh scales and all
that within that
so i mean i could speak for hours about
this but you know yeah so that's what i
can
say in in brief very very fascinating
topic and very good question sir thanks
thank you so much thank you so much sir
bye nice meeting you nice meeting you
all right let's bring in some more
people
let us bring in
who's ready
are we all ready
let us bring in shrey
good evening sir
[Music]
foreign
okay let me just address both the
questions uh there is no real evidence
that the nazis told indian ideas and
made plains with that
evidence
i mean lots of theories are there like
right so we cannot make the claim some
people make the claim but it is a
baseless claim without any evidence
yes it is an enormous
piece of architecture an entire city
made out of stone
it is it was a hindu temple initially it
was a temple dedicated to
vishnu to lord vishnu and then
so it used to be a vishnu temple
eventually it was transformed into a
buddhist temple because buddha is also
regarded as
vishnu
and see
so it is not really any any big change
so that's what it was uh
i think it uh
the city was abandoned because of
climate change and
about seven eight hundred years ago and
so on so yeah that's what it was now uh
if the french instead of the french the
british had found it would they have
allowed it to be discovered or to be to
be made public i don't know possibly
they may have they would not really care
about that
or india may say but everybody temple
complexes thick i mean definitely north
india northern india temple complexes
foreign
yes
thank you so much for the question nice
meeting you sir thank you bye
all right who else do we have let's
bring in
all right nice to meet you
thank you thank you sir
so my question is that
we have seen that you know today
everybody
propaganda is that we did not have good
uh a great glorious past and the counter
propaganda is that we had a great
glorious past
so my question is what will it enable
our people you know
uh what what will the people today get
by recognizing our true history what
will we achieve out of it
because that's very good
okay what you don't understand is that
what will be achieved by recognizing our
true history see if you uh
what you think about yourself and your
ancestors from the past is what
determines how you see yourself today if
you feel if if a little if a small child
feels that his or her ancestors were
great and glorious people it imbues that
child with a certain sense of self
confidence that we can do things we can
achieve things we can take on challenges
and we can
we can surmount those challenges now if
you tell a child that their ancestors
are
a lineage of losers
that mentality seeps in and they will
not take on any big challenges right so
it's all about creating a certain idea a
certain self image
in the child and that's why his the the
entire marxist colonial project of
distorting history
had a social engineering agenda to
turn indians
into docile losers
everybody speaks about india the
slave-mindedness of indians indians have
the slave mentality this is where it
comes from
right but what was that what did they
achieve by making us do side what was
their final aim
has india emerged as a superpower today
after 70 years of independence
right
that's what they achieved india has all
the potential in the world
to become the number one nation in terms
of economy in terms of culture in terms
of military everything technology
everything india has we all know this
sir you also know it mr mandar that we
indians
have the potential to to surpass
everybody in every sphere of excellence
why are we not doing it
one of the reasons is this
that we don't believe
that we are capable of doing that
because we have not been taught our
truest
that's as simple as it is
right
makes sense
yes of course
very nice thank you thank you so much
for the question nice meeting you sir
thank you thank you yeah bye
all right let us bring in
somebody else
uh whom shall we bring it let's bring in
krishna
good evening ma'am
nice to meet you what's your question
ma'am
sir many times we feel um
feel that this movement is repeating
and um
many times you feel that
this movement is repeating again and
again
um it really i repeat or it is our
mindset
okay uh which movement are you referring
to
yeah means uh
last few days i am
i
[Music]
foreign
movement
it is
that is not my field of expertise i have
certainly heard of this it's a
fascinating thing many not many people
some people experience this and they
they
feel that things have happened in the
past and we are seeing it again so i'm
not sure what it is you know i think
we need to invite some psychologists
psychiatrist or neurologist to discuss
this phenomenon which is fascinating it
certainly exists but i don't know what
is the reason for it i don't know what
causes this thing
but i can confirm that it certainly
exists and some and some people a
certain percentage of the population
does report experiencing this so that's
what i can tell you man
one more little
the claim of the first airplane was made
by us
one question per person
please please follow the rules thank you
so much
we have to treat everybody the same
right
all right
thank you so much for your question nice
meeting you nice to meet you
yeah bye-bye
okay
let's bring in somebody else let's who
has been waiting for a while
has someone been waiting for a while uh
let's bring mr ayush hello
hi hi
namaste
namaste have you been on this show
before
no sir
you have not first time no sir first one
no okay okay very nice very nice okay
where are you from
india
very nice very nice so what's your
question sir sir my question is sir does
india have more
dinosaur fossils than china or any other
asian country
but still but till did not been
discovered
yes oh that's a fascinating question
paleontology
so uh
india does have uh deposits of dinosaur
fossils because we have found uh a
tyrannosaurid dinosaur fossils in the
narmada valley
a dinosaur that was similar to the
tyrannosaurus rex dinosaur which is from
north america
and we have discovered dinosaur eggs
also in various parts of india so
certainly we do have
uh fossils of dinosaurs in india
the thing is that in china they have
turned this into an industry because
they want to use it for the purpose of
tourism and to show their expertise in
this field and they have been able to
discover lots of new species of
dinosaurs because they have been looking
for it they are actively looking for it
they have active paleontology
departments and
initiatives in china
and that's why they have been able to
discover so many dinosaur fossils and
new species and so on they've even
discovered dinosaurs whose feathers are
preserved and even the color of the
feathers is preserved right because
dinosaurs most dinosaurs had feathers
dinosaurs and birds are the same thing
now about india
there is not a as far as i know there is
not a single paleontology department in
this country there is not a single
institute of paleontology in the country
i think india could have as many if not
more
deposits of dinosaur fossils than china
i mean people stumble upon these remains
from time to time and they are just
neglected like everything else in india
the government neglects everything
i think it could be something that we
could exploit
uh
in uh attracting tourism you know
creating dinosaur theme parks like
jurassic park and all that i'm not
saying we should recreate living
dinosaurs but we could create these
dinosaur theme parks and all that
to attract tourists and it could add uh
something into you know to our tourism
arsenal and all and it could also throw
light upon this the science of of
understanding our past the the past of
our planet because the dinosaur era was
a very significant era
and maybe there were some species of
dinosaurs that were only endemic to
india when india was part of the african
land mass and so on so it is something
that should be taken up i really wonder
why india doesn't take doesn't take up
any of these initiatives when this is
just low-hanging fruit we we have
everything here we have the dinosaur
fossils and all that
so unfortunately as of today we have
done nothing we don't know how many
species species of dinosaurs were there
in india clearly there were many
very good question
can you hear me yes sir
yes i guess
all right nice question thank you so
much nice meeting you
yes
thank you
thank you bye-bye
all right let us bring in
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
ronesh kumar
hello sir
i cannot hear you sir
can you hear me now i can hear you now
yes okay
okay
i've been doing many things
just okay
last question maybe
we are not really uh
promoting our uh tourism we are not
really going into all those research
into music and all s
okay right now we all say that india has
the uh
biggest youth power what he care that is
the thing but that's not always gonna be
the case because uh it's some time it is
going to become a bigger
india can never be a superpower like
south korea and japan keeping the size
smaller
so they don't have to cover the negative
in geopolitics practical way of doing
things
population
problems what is the most practical and
effective solution for this going
forward
yes a very very good question very
important question log bold india's
population is a demographic dividend it
is a nice way of portraying the
portraying it and trying to make light
not make light of the problem but you
know
trying to keep a positive approach and
outlook for the people
but like there are negatives as well and
a lot many and sorry for interrupting
yourself yeah no not really so what i
the way i perceive india's population of
1.3 billion people i perceive it as a
potential demographic disaster
such a such an enormous population is an
enormous burden on the resources of the
subcontinent of india
we have to look back in time just 70
years since about 70 years ago before
india was partitioned the total
population of undivided india was about
330 million
that is one-fourth of what only india's
population is today so you can imagine
the burden on the resources of the
country so this was the the consequence
of the nehru and policy of extraordinary
poverty or the narrowing rate of growth
so people had to produce i mean whenever
a nation is extremely poor the growth
rate of population increases
exponentially so that's what we see
throughout the world
and that's why india's population grew
so much
now what needs to be done i mean
certainly we need to tackle this problem
now we cannot
eliminate the population overnight i
mean that doesn't work and a one-child
policy also is going to create a
demographic disaster china is now going
into
a phase in which the majority of the
population is going to be elderly
so that is going to be another
demographic disaster in china so we
cannot try to even think about such a
policy of one of having or forcing every
couple to have only one child
what we can do is we can uh
give people a reason to have not more
than two children i mean if if a couple
has two children or less than give them
certain incentives or something
uh some some
government stops or whatever i mean the
government needs to come up with
creative ideas to
to make it uh
to make people want to have not more
than two kids i think if we have a
two-child policy
then i think at least the population
will be stabilized and it will not grow
it will not keep on growing the weight
it is growing right now so that is
something that we need to find a
solution to
certainly because we cannot have a
population of 1.3 million 1.4 million
1.5 million it's going to be an enormous
burden on the country and eventually on
the whole world so even uh 1.3 yeah they
because like so many people are now
coming illegally into india that might
be much more
or from government perspective even if i
think even if say whoever is in the
power even if they can
people will not take it positively and
they might not come into the power
maybe for 10 15 years so even they will
not push it because everyone wants to be
in the power right and from the people
level i don't know how much time they it
will take them to realize and by that
time it might be too late so like we
might we are so many people lack of
resources and then so and like a lot of
fights because like same in the metro
about me happened
there are 10 people and 20 seats so you
people are well behaved because i know
okay i can easily get a seat but in
delhi metro there is only one seat 20
people so they just like run after each
other like animals so same thing
yes yes it's it's a very big problem i
mean it causes unnecessary scarcity of
resources uh there is always this rush
for resources there's competition so
everybody instead of cooperating is
competing against each other and so on
so this is a problem that needs to be
tackled it has to be a long term
solution it will not happen in the next
10 20 years maybe we have to have a 50
year plan or so
but it needs to be tackled we need to
somehow find a way
within the next hundred years to go back
to at least below 500 million if that is
possible
so if you take a long-term approach then
you may be able to plant better and like
you said we have all these illegal
immigrants and all which is a big
problem so
yeah this is a big problem for india we
we need to find out
we cannot think of becoming superpower
because we will be depleted internally
so we will be a fake superpower
yeah i agree oh good observation so much
uh thank you so much for having me and
uh one thing i wanted to tell the
viewers because that was that's what i
uh observed last time
thank you so much nice meeting you sir
thank you bye-bye
all right let us bring in
somebody else
let's bring in somebody else uh i would
like somebody who has
not been here before let's bring in mr
pierce
good evening sir
so
very nice so what's your question sir
uh sir i have a question
it is related to a previous question but
a little bit uh so do you think
conversion based on love
could be used as a tool to change the
demographics
uh sorry i missed the last part what was
that conversion based on love
can be can it be used as a tool to
change demographics
there are all kinds of tools that are
used to change demographics in the in
this country there are all kinds of
projects going on so yes certainly it's
one of the tools i agree
and do you think that the term
so the term which is used in media that
is love
j and do you think it's real or it is uh
consistent with the today's scenario
i think it is something everybody knows
about even the media is speaking about
it so i don't think i have anything
extra to add to it everybody knows that
certain things exist
right
so yeah
answer and a follow-up question related
to it sir so do you think it can
know
this question uh contains that question
do you think it can lead to existential
anxiety
i don't know what existential anxiety is
what is that could you define that
so if we
see the demographic change around us and
we see that the culture is uh
more foreign than it is uh inherent to
the india then do you think that it can
leads to anxiety related to and
eventually it can lead to civil war
yes
[Music]
right can you hear me
yes sir
all right any
yes
he said do you got any questions sir
the link was interesting
i am not able to hear you sir
sir do you think that
said do you think that the culture if it
which is in india if it becomes more
foreign
one question per person so you are
asking multiple questions
i need to treat everybody the same so
okay so uh so
all right let's bring in somebody else
what happened here
okay uh let's bring in a vinay
hi vinay
jain
how are you
sir i wanna i want to ask that
india india never
india never uh
speaks about he speaks on chinese
sovereignty
and uh chinese always claims arunachal
pradesh and various and they have sucks
graham valley also
so sir i have a question that if india
corroborates
yes sir
yes
so sir if india corroborates taiwan and
tibet as independent country and openly
rejects one china policy
so sir what consequences we have to face
from the chinese
economic consequences
well
yes sorry i think there's a problem from
my side yes please continue your
question yes sir so i'm asking that if
india
accepts taiwan and tibet as independent
countries and rejects one china policy
so what economic consequences or
any other trade consequences we have to
face from the chinese are these
consequences normal
we are making too much of it or it will
affect indian economy by a very high
margin
right that's a very good question so
what are the consequences we can face if
we were to uh
reject the one china policy recognize
taiwan as a country and declare that
tibet is not a part of china
or there could be a whole bunch of
consequences see the chinese uh have
infiltrated the entire global economic
system the power uh structures of the
world the united nations the who as we
know these are
this is something they have been working
on for the past three to four decades so
they have infiltrated every country they
have infiltrated the united nations all
the global institutions the who the
world bank they have even infiltrated
deep into the united states and the
western countries
so they have a very strong hold on the
global economy they are very much part
of every single network in the global
economy all the supply chains everything
they are so much into
they have a stranglehold on the
manufacturing uh worldwide manufacturing
process and all that so it is something
that they have this enormous economic
might they have this enormous economic
might and because their economy has
grown so much that gdp is so high they
also have been able to develop a very
powerful military so if india were to
dis
were able to if india were to reject the
one china policy and so so on then it
they could bring to for to bear a whole
lot of consequences on india
the
there could be problems at the u.n level
there could be problems from uh
from other countries they could induce
other countries to to
do certain things that are not in
india's favor and they could also try
and create trouble on the border they
may they may even try to launch a short
sharp war or something so they have an
entire toolkit at their disposal and the
thing is that they could uh because of
their much larger economic uh stature
and might they can impose costs on india
that would be
uh
kind of you could look upon them as
economic sanctions for instance when
india did the nuclear tests in 1998 the
americans imposed economic sanctions on
india which
uh because of which india was not able
to acquire certain technologies it it
set india's technological development
back by at least a decade so that is an
example of economic sanctions the
chinese could also do such things india
needs certain uh
certain uh
what do you call them certain parts you
know spares and all that from china
certain uh semiconductors certain
chips and so on which are only
manufactured in china they could cut off
those supplies and so on so there's a
whole lot of things they can do right we
don't want to get into that right now
india doesn't want to enter into that
sort of conflict with china right now
india needs to spend the next 10 years
at least
building up its economy
once you cross the 10 trillion dollar
mark then you have a certain stature and
perhaps then you can think of
taking china on see the chinese the
statesman deng xiaoping had a very clear
policy
his policy was
uh
keep your capabilities hidden and bide
your time and work on building your
strength
right so that's what he exhorted the
chinese to do and that's where that's
the direction in which he steered china
so from the 1980s onward until the 2010s
the chinese just kept quiet they did not
showcase and show off their capabilities
they just kept on building building
building and then after xi jinping took
over that's when they started their
moves
so india needs to
take a similar approach right now
there's no point entering into
unnecessary conflicts with china right
now just to give them lip service said
that yes we believe in this so-called
one china policy even if they try they
keep on needling us in arunachal pradesh
in other places
right now
just swallow the insults build up your
strength go to gym build up a huge
physique and then you take them on right
so that's the approach india needs to
take
so this is the reason why government is
very calm and we should support the
government instead of
we should understand that there are
things that we don't know about there
are things far below the surface that
the government knows but we they are not
visible to all of us so we have to
support the government no matter what
happens especially when the government
has done well in the terms of in terms
of foreign policy etc in the past few
years so we need to support the
government and and
that that's the best way to take the
country forward
right
thank you
thank you for the question very good
question nice meeting you
jai hind bye
all right let us bring in somebody who
has been waiting for a while let me see
who all are here
um who is there let me bring in
atharva
hello sir
hello
sir it's really good that you talked
about hindustani classical music
recently in previous questions
unfortunately your sound is lagging
i'm not able to hear you sir
just a second please try again oops gone
it's gone
oh no
okay until he comes back hopefully let's
bring in somebody else let me bring in
let me bring in mr shiv
hello
can't hear you please unmute
yourself hello sir hi
i can hear you yes sir yes sir uh sir
first of all i'm very glad to see you
that uh afternoon
after waiting so long i i got a chance
to talk with you sir i had one question
regarding my theologies that uh in uh
means very long second i talk in hindi
india
yes
uh
or greek pantheon or roman pantheon or
nordic pantheon or uh
and the culture also spread across the
world right
so i'm gonna mute you because
okay i'm gonna mute you okay thank you
so much
thank you right so about here so the
culture essentially was the same
pura agar app eurasia from india to all
the way to the west to the uh irish to
the british islands you had the same
culture essentially you had lots of
beautiful local manifestations of the
same culture
s
from the desert regions of uh
of judea
present-day israel
the so-called abrahamic culture the
abrahamic religions which are
monotheistic traditions
for some reason whatever it is it is a
extremely expansionist kind of uh
kind of
tradition it is it is
it is a culture or a
religious system that is expansionist it
is supremacist
it is exclusivist these are known facts
you can read their books and this is
right there's nothing controversial that
i'm saying there
now
he was the
emperor in constantinople
he saw this as an opportunity
to uh
to consolidate his hold on the empire so
he he
declared christianity to be the official
state religion of the roman empire
and that precipitated and accelerated
the conversion of the people into
christianity and because it is a
monotheistic monolithic culture it was
it it made it easier for him to exercise
total control over his subjects and over
his empire
so from a political perspective from a
cold hard political
uh
perspective monotheistic cultures and
religions are
much better in controlling the people
that's why politicians are the ones who
started the conversion process so that's
what we saw
in the roman empire
and then you saw the spread of
christianity very fast across europe
even the vikings were subjugated and
converted to christianity
and it was still a rather brutal process
the conversion of europe to christianity
was brutal uh you can read the book by
catherine nixie the darkening age in
which she has detailed
uh she has given lots of details about
how the old
indigenous culture of europe was
destroyed by force and christianity was
imposed upon europe and similarly with
the other the other major abrahamic
religion which is islam again it spread
through through similar means i mean
there is no controversy in the way in
how it spread
some people claim that it spread by
voluntary conversion well that is not
really the case right
so the real reason why uh rulers like to
adopt monotheistic religions is that
these are militaristic in nature
and it gives them a better way of
controlling the people and whatever
regions they rule so that's the reason
why it it became very popular right make
sense sir sir just one request uh sir
please uh add more of the videos on the
channel because uh my family members
also watches them but they are they are
a lot uh
easier to
get knowledge in hindi yes sir
okay i will try and invest some time in
that all right sir thank you so much for
the question
nice meeting you thank you thank you
bye-bye
all right let us bring in
somebody else
um
whom shall i bring in let us bring in a
sagar
hello sagar
could you please unmute yourself
am i audible no
yes sir you are audible okay where are
you from
so sir i'm from pune
thanks for bringing me so my question
revolves around uh a very controversial
topic
and i am not sure if i should uh
name that uh on the video maybe the
youtube algorithm might
catch it and maybe man your videos but
it revolves around the plant which is
bad i guess you might have got it now
and the plant is banned
like since 1985 i guess so like what was
the reason for that and
uh
like i have few examples from my friend
circles and you know
uh elsewhere i can
get to get this news like that plant has
helped many people
and
you know there are some benefits but
when people go and talk about those
benefits
the person who is listening it's like
you know uh no that's really
uh you know a weird thing and they don't
believe it so like what's your take on
that uh plant and why was it banned in
india and why all of a sudden
okay okay good question i don't see any
controversy in that you're referring to
the cannabis plant marijuana ganja
whatever you want to call it right
that's what you're referring to no
controversy there i think you're right i
think it was banned sometime in 1985 or
something like that i don't know why it
was banned
it is a natural substance it is a plant
that has been
used for thousands of years in india
and it is not some synthetic drug that
is addictive or something i'm sure if
you smoke something there's going to be
some effect
but it's not like smoking some hard drug
or something and it's been something
that has been part of india's traditions
mystical traditions and so on i i know
that certain sadhus they they'd like to
consume that or smoke that or whatever
and in recent times research has
demonstrated that the active compound in
this plant seems to have very beneficial
effects even the non-psychoactive
compound thc i think it's called
i think that also has a i'm not sure if
it's thc or something else
there are a number of compounds in there
but there is a non-psychoactive
component of
the plant which has a very beneficial
effect and
it is good for
calming people down people who have
depression or anxiety it calms them down
it relaxes them i think even people who
are suffering from some
people who have chronic pain etc they
would benefit from consuming or or
partaking of
of this plant and so on so i don't think
it is
something that should be regarded as a
hard drug or as a narcotic
it is a naturally occurring plant and i
i am not sure about this but i have
heard i think somewhere that it is not
really addictive
so if you have it once you're not gonna
want to have it every day if somebody
smokes uh tobacco for instance
uh they get they get hooked to it they
get addicted and it's i know that it's
it's extremely difficult for people who
are smokers to quit the habit it's so
hard you know because it is i think it
is even more addictive than heroin or
cocaine or something that's what i heard
and similarly with alcohol people who
get into the habit of drinking alcohol
they simply can't acquit it right
so in the case of cannabis in the case
of marijuana that is not the case i mean
i'm not an expert that but this is what
i've heard
so i don't see why this plant has been
banned in india i think it's just a case
of copying and aping the west
in the west they had banned this plant
so we should also be civilized enough to
follow the west and do whatever the hell
they're doing
and now in the u.s there is this
movement to legalize the use of cannabis
in the netherlands i think it's been
legal for quite some time now many
states in the u.s have decriminalized
the use of this uh plant
and in india it's been part of our
traditions for thousands of years so i
think it is it is just going backwards
to blindly copy what the west is doing
and and
criminalize the use of this plant i i
i think the uh
the authorities the law enforcement
authorities
i think they are reasonably lenient when
it comes to the use of cannabis
uh
so it is kind of you know oh kind of
tolerated
and they may not
they may not really punish people or
throw them into jail for using it if
unless they do it all the time but i
think it's it's pointless i think we
need to decriminalize the the
the use of uh this plant because it does
have
uh
positive effects on some people people
uh who who suffer from like what i said
you know depression anxiety etc and so
on so i think it's something that the
government should take up and consider
you know yeah
okay thanks sir
all right nice meeting nice meeting you
thanks thanks
bye
all right
let us see
i can see mr ajit has been waiting for
quite some time let us bring in mr ajit
hello sir yeah hello sir hello sir good
evening
good night thanks for adding me in this
call i was waiting for class from last
four session
so
i have one question and this is
regarding the role of mr doctor
obviously
i mean how do you see the role of dr
babasham bakker in shaping the indian
society after our called independence
i mean did he fought for the social
justice or
was his mindsets were just a result of
british colony
and uh
and have we actually been leaked to the
that kind of society where social
justice is actually in place or
i mean he was uh still a believer of
iron invasion theory from his writing we
can see
in his book
we can see he was believer of our
invasion theory and that's why
most of his followers and
uh panther so-called panthers they are
following the same and
i mean lots of problems are happening
in our society because of that
so right good question how do you see
stories
right so i'll tell you something until
2016 or 2017 i used to believe in the r
invasion theory
i i myself used to believe it right
because this is what we were taught and
in the 1955
40s 50s everybody believed in this
theory because nobody had found the
evidence that totally proves it wrong
so i have nothing against people from 70
80 100 years ago etc believing in the
invasion theory
that this used to believe in it he wrote
a book about this it's not his fault it
is it was the prevailing wisdom at the
time it was the accepted wisdom so that
is fine that is not an issue now when it
comes to mr ambedkar you know truthfully
i haven't studied his life in any detail
i have never really been interested in
the
period of time in which this so-called
freedom struggle happened because it was
very clear to me from the very beginning
that it's a fake freedom struggle
and i have never really found mr
ambedkar that interesting i'm not
thinking he's not a great figure or
whatever i don't know i don't know much
about him i have never
invested the time in studying his life
and his writings and all because i
to be very frank and honest i found it
rather dull
what has interested me in my life is
the
ancient indian history the harappan
times the vedic times etc and i i have
always looked upon history as a big
picture project i have studied the
history of the entire world but if you
ask me the history of a particular
dynasty somewhere then i may not know
about it but i know the big picture
sequence and chronology of the history
of the world and i know the
major players in that now i am not sure
about the role of mr ambedkar how
significant it was
and how great of a figure he was when it
comes to indian history i know that he
was very much anti-mohandas gandhi he
had a very low opinion of mr gandhi so
that is what i know i know that he is
given the credit credit of framing
india's constitution uh i don't know
actually if he actually wrote the
constitution himself or not but he was
the the head of the committee that wrote
this
so
i i really cannot give a judgment about
mr ambedkar
whether he was
a significant and towering figure like
many people claim he was i really don't
know i haven't studied his life in that
much detail because i have never found
it that interesting to be very honest it
doesn't mean that other people should
not find it interesting everybody has
their own
uh
you know
their own thing which they like or not
like that much
so my what has driven my study of
history is overall big picture history
i have not studied
many individuals i mean i have not
studied every individual that has that
has existed i have studied the great
drivers of history but not everybody so
unfortunately i cannot answer your
question in great detail but
that's where we are yeah
thank you sir i mean just one question
um based on that subject only i mean uh
who are the great figures from the
indian history in last thousands here uh
i mean
like you said in your last sessions
lord ram lord krishna the gotham buddha
certainly great
mr
vardhaman mahavir was great kanishka the
great many kings and queens of mythology
they call them mythical and etc you know
they try to term them as mythical kings
or queens like the great vikram emperor
vikramaditya come on man that's nonsense
then the great gupta emperors like like
skanda gupta
the karkota dynasty like
the peda
was great and so on so there are so many
great figures that i cannot you know i
cannot think of remember all of them
right now i'm sure i've missed many but
there have been many many very
significant
uh stalwarts in indian history who have
built up this great civilization over
over thousands of years right
yeah thank you thanks
thank you for your question nice meeting
you sir nice meeting you
thank you thanks
all right let us bring in mr khabir
bisla who has been waiting for some time
hello sir
hello hello where are you from
some merit
merit all right sir what's your question
sir my question is as the turkic
invaders or so-called mughals invaded
india they brought islam with them
and the islam destroyed our culture in
our ancestral areas like punjab and
sindh in pakistan so how can we restore
our culture in these areas
what we can do see what you are stating
is correct as you know today there is no
indian culture in these regions there is
a
there is a fact there is no controversy
in that right
what can we do
we need to revive our culture in our our
own territory right now
even today in in 2021 india's culture is
waning it is declining i mean people are
deracinated they have forgotten their
roots
right
our religions our festivals are being
banned
countrywide
we are not allowed to practice our
festivals we are not allowed to
administer our own
religious
sites like temples
the wealth that is donated to temples by
devotees is stolen by the government and
used by god use for god knows what means
what purposes and so on
so first of all we need to revive we
need to protect and revive our culture
our traditions in our own
land that we currently administer that
is the first stage
and when it comes to sindh and punjab of
pakistan and gandhar and all that that
is that has to be a long term project
maybe the next 100 years the next 200
years we don't see we are a very ancient
civilization more than 10 000 years old
our plans don't end with one lifetime
our plans have to span centuries
we are simply one link in the long chain
and we have to ensure that the chain
continues it is not broken
so right now we are in the situation
is it possible to revive our culture in
civilization certainly it is possible as
as long as we all get together and work
in the same common direction and as long
as we are united we will succeed
so to answer the question we need to
first do it in india
yes sir so the indian government uh
their policies are very anti-india
yes yes absolutely how it is
to certify it
yeah so so today if you look at india
it's india is the world's most hindu
phobic country india hindus have more
equal rights in the west than in india
in india hindus are second class
citizens india is a hindu phobic
apartheid state by its constitution by
its laws by its policies by its
government's governance
by its institutions everything
everything is in the phobic so we need
to
we need to
find good leaders i'm not saying the
current the current leadership is not
good but the current leadership is
is in a situation where the entire
structure is hindu phobic so they have
to take
one step small step at a time i i think
that's the reason why things are slow
but we need to ensure that we develop
great leaders among our youth among
people like you because you guys are
going to be the future leaders of india
so that's what india needs to do we need
to understand what leadership is what is
leadership today nobody understands like
a leadership nobody knows
leadership is not having a big voice
leadership is not being tall leadership
is something else we have to understand
what that is and we also have to
understand what is the national interest
today we are not taught these things in
school college university what is
leadership what is national interest
once we start understanding these things
we will go in the right direction right
so it's a it's a long process but it is
certainly feasible
right
yes thank you
nice meeting you sir thank you for the
question thank you bye
all right
let me bring in
whom shall i bring in i shall bring in
mr sushrut
hello sir hello sir
how are you doing
sir good
yes sir what's your question
sir uh there are many similarities
between the greek culture and the indian
culture
if we go long back
so so is that possible that the dwarka
is actually
the atlantis described by the plateau
that's a very interesting uh theory that
you just put forth you know what um yeah
so the so i think this guy plateau he
wrote about this city called
atlantis that sank into the ocean
because of a powerful earthquake and
everything just disappeared under the
sea
now
the europeans believe that it was in the
ocean between europe and the americas so
they called it the atlantic ocean
but they have never discovered any such
place
where such an event happened they've
never discovered a city that is under
that has gone underwater
the only city that we know of that has
uh undergone such an event
a catastrophic earthquake and
going under the sea is dwarka
so that is absolutely true so and
until very recently historians used to
say that this story of dwarka from the
mahabharata times that this earthquake
happened and the city was followed by
the ocean it is just just it's just a
myth we used to keep saying that
until in the 1980s i think
our archaeologists discovered an entire
city
under the ocean
right off the coast of modern day dwarka
so clearly this is something that
actually happened what is described in
the mahabharata that arjuna was there
and he's always happened it actually
happened because we now have the
evidence
so is this the atlantis that plato spoke
about well it is called dwarka we have
never called it atlanta so we don't know
about that
but it's the only place in the world
where such an event has happened so
maybe plato was referring to this place
with a different name it is possible but
we don't have the evidence to
to uh
to create a definitive connection
between these two things but yeah it's a
good hypothesis certainly we could we
can take it seriously and consider it
right
okay sir sir can i request you for a
video
please tell me
sir uh actually if we go and look at
ayurveda it was the best source of
medicines so can you just tell in a
video that about the origins of ayurveda
and how it progressed
that's a that's a very interesting topic
i will certainly uh
put that on my to-do list
right
okay thank you so much nice meeting
thank you thank you sir thank you thank
you bye-bye
all right all right let me bring in uh
whom shall i bring in let me bring in mr
mr sushant
hello sir thank you sir
namaste sir
civilization
the carbon dating what i need like it is
certainly something that was there for
several centuries
or that was the text of the artist
i'm sure in our great universities
which was discovered
about i think in the late 18th century
or early 19th century and that's how we
were able to rediscover the arthashastra
which is popularly known as chanakyaniti
so
like interpretation
in the corporate world etc so it can be
used certainly in these things military
strategy etc is applicable in all
domains of life in personal life in
business life and family life
in geopolitics everywhere so yeah
thank
and it should be reintegrated completely
with india
and it should be indian it is indian it
is it will always be indian
and we need to reintegrate the entirety
of kashmir with with the nation of india
that's what needs to happen and we need
to eliminate terrorism and all the
nonsense right yes thank you sir
thank you nice meeting you bye
all right let us bring in
mr prabhudata
hello sir
hello hello
hello yeah hi yes hi i can hear you
uh
okay there uh i am
i am from
okay
so so my question is uh
can't we simplify our religion
under religious texts like
you know there are so many texts in our
interview
so can't we just simplify like abrahamic
relations
and
so
my question is that can't we just
simplify it for our you know
today's era so that our
our population
simplify
so that everybody will understand it
properly and everybody will get united
this is something that has been
discussed and taken up for a very long
time reforming hinduism
so the thing is that uh
it is
if you if you try to reform hinduism and
oh and simplify it then we lose the
essence of hinduism hinduism is
it is about 10 000 plus years old
tradition
sophistication or complexity
and it is a very liberal
pluralistic
tradition
point of view
hinduism is not a religion it is a
culture it is a civilizational thing
the abrahamic religions are monotheistic
religions which is totally different but
you are right because of our complexity
and diversity there is no unity you are
that that point is correct
so make it
instead of trying to simplify hinduism
we need to create a leadership structure
that everybody everybody recognizes and
follows and then that leader i mean that
has to be real leadership not just say
fake leadership right
everybody becomes a guru
yoga class
so we have to understand the real gurus
are very different they are really
accomplished people so
instead i i would say that instead of
trying to simplify hinduism we need to
create a proper organizational structure
and a real leadership
agreement
until that happens
unity is not not really possible right
that's what that's my pleasure
thank you sir and uh
thank you thank you so much for you for
your kind words thank you so much i
really appreciate it
thank you g thank you
bye
all right who else do we have
whom shall i bring in let me bring in mr
soviet
soviet roy
hello sir hello hello am i audible
yes sir you are audible so i'm from west
bengal uh my question is on
science and or and or spirituality and
in a spiritual discourse i uh listened
about the fact that
space has been generated from
time
and time is from a greater time like
like that so i want to know about your
take from the viewpoint of modern
science
is this relevant in a modern viewpoint
of fans as well
like uh yeah it was a video of sad guru
santa cruz he said that
because there is time
so there is space so space is kind of uh
evolved from time
and time is from and there is a greater
time concept so i want to know your
okay i get it right i get what you're
asking uh interesting question so i am
not familiar with the theories of
satguruji i have i'm not familiar with
that
uh so he's saying that uh space emerges
from time
so it is time that exists first and out
of time space comes out yes so that's an
interesting yeah i get it right so it's
an interesting theory but uh
we we have no evidence of that right i
mean
the thing is this see
satguruji is not a scientist he's a he
is more into the realm of philosophy
right philosophy and spirituality that
is that is where he comes from
i believe this is the context from
indian spirituality
i get it i get it right so
so we have a
number of
philosophical schools of thought we have
atomism that came from maharishi kanada
which can be viewed as the first quantum
theory of the first atomic theory in
which there is a certain set of
principles that governs the world and
there are a whole
bunch of other
spiritual and philosophical schools of
thought now it is
well known that physics especially
science and physics they emerged out of
philosophy
but there is a there is a set of rules
that comes with fi with science and
physics and those rules don't really
apply when it comes to philosophy for
instance when we talk about physics
physics
deals with observables
it deals with physical objects and
physical phenomena observable objects in
observable phenomena
in philosophy you can deal with
you can discuss
non-observable non-physical objects in
phenomena like the soul i mean we have
never ever been able to take a
photograph of the soul or weigh the soul
or measure the soul or observe it so the
physical uh when it comes to science and
when it comes to philosophy these two do
not mix
so in philosophy in spirituality you can
make theories that
may never be observable may never be
verifiable but you can make these uh you
can have these theories these are
philosophical theories but they are not
necessarily scientific theories so from
the perspective of science you need
evidence observational evidence
and from that perspective as a scientist
i have to tell you that there is no
actual observational evidence that space
emerges from time now in physics there
is the big bang theory
in which there was a singularity which
gave rise to the entire universe
space-time emerged of it
but we don't know what caused the the
initial
expansion of space-time so we know what
happened but we don't know why it
happened so even science does not have
lots of answers we have to understand
that so there are big gaps in our
understanding of science
and that's where philosophy could
possibly give us some kind of marga
darshan so to say show us the direction
especially indian philosophy because
when you go deep deep deep into the
cutting edge of science where
where possibility meets reality that's
where you realize that we don't have
many answers and that's where
quantum physicists etc they have
invariably been attracted towards indian
philosophy because indian philosophy
does talk does talk about the strange
phenomena that are as strange as the
phenomena that quantum physics throws up
you know
so
to answer your question uh i don't know
if space emerges from time because we
have no evidence but
it is something we should certainly
consider because there is nothing that
proves that it doesn't emerge from time
so yeah
also one thing to mention here that
einstein also said that
there is a time swiss bend so we do not
know what is beyond that bend
there is a
time
yeah he was referring to the curvature
of space time which is caused by mass
mass curves space time space time tells
mass how to move there is general
relativity which is all thanks to mr
albert einstein
and yeah he had certain views in about
uh things that uh go somewhat beyond
science once a scientist goes beyond a
certain age they start dabbling into
philosophy and spirituality and all that
so it is at that stage that they mention
such things but there is no evidence for
that see as a scientist you have to
maintain the discipline that you only
accept things before which there is
evidence observational evidence that is
the limitation that all scientists have
now if you go if you talk beyond that
you're not no longer talking science you
are either talking philosophy or
religion or spirituality
or something yeah all that yeah that's
what it is
right okay thank you for giving me this
okay good night
thank you so much very nice meeting you
thanks bye
right all right who has been waiting for
a while
there's a bunch of people okay let me
bring in mr
suyog hello sir hello sir
sir so uh so my question is uh sir
actually i have a lot of argument
with respect to roads versus trains so
we have many developed country countries
who have adopted different approaches
right so for example the us has adopted
roads china as well
while on the other hand japan has
adopted trains a lot of trains so i was
i wanted to ask about what is more
beneficial about
in
in case of india because you know we can
only invest a certain fixed amount of
money on one of these infrastructures at
a time so right now mr gatkar is
focusing on roads and he you know wants
to adopt the us model but i think uh you
know there are certain inherent
differences between indian terrain and
that of the us so i wanted to know your
opinion roads versus trade yes
that's a that's a very good question
very good question so i think that um
a country of india's size and india's
population
needs excellent mass transportation
so in the u.s what you have is that even
if you go wanna go to
go to the neighborhood grocery shop you
will go by car
that's how it is
people don't walk people just don't walk
there they always do everything by
by hopping into a car
so that is a very inefficient way of
doing things because it burns so much
fuel it contributes to so much pollution
it eats up so many resources of our
planet but the us has been blessed with
with this enormous continent that they
have captured
from the natives and therefore they're
hell bent on exploiting it and that's
why they have the certain this
particular lifestyle everything is
disposable everything is to be used and
exploited as a resource in the case of
india
we have a population of 1.3 billion we
have a very large subcontinent sized uh
geography but we have to utilize it
effectively and when you have so many
people you don't want all of them to get
into cars or even auto rickshaws or
whatever because it's going to cause so
much pollution so you need to develop
efficient means of mass transportation
so if people want to travel either you
put them on planes one plane has a bunch
of people in there 100 200 people and
transport them or you need to develop
an efficient rail network high-speed
rail network that will
that will uh facilitate transportation
which is i think something india is
already pursuing in the past few years a
decade or so
india is certainly investing in the
railway network the railway network is
increasing now it is
expanding
i think since the british left uh left
india until the early 2010s i think
there was almost no change in the number
of railway lines we had
right so now we are significantly
pursuing the expansion of the railway
network and we are also pursuing the
expansion of our roadways and all
because when you are transporting goods
via trucks and all roads are certainly
necessary so i think what the government
is doing it is uh pursuing a
multi-pronged strategy we are opening
lots of new airports
lots of small towns are getting airports
now so people will get to be will be
able to transport we'll be able to
travel because of that so that is an
efficient means of travel you know lots
of people on one aircraft so
that is good
railways need to be expanded especially
the freight traffic freight
railroads and all that and roads so i
think india is ensuring that all these
different ways of traveling and
transportation are being opened up
because this country needs to grow
economy needs to grow so i think it is
useful for all of this to happen but in
my opinion
it is
always beneficial to invest in high
quality
mass transit systems
like railways
and even metro systems and all that and
and high quality buses instead of having
people travel on two wheelers and three
wheelers and four wheelers it's always
better to have high quality mass
transportation
so
i think
yeah so on behalf of because most of
your uh i i don't know if it's true most
of the watchers are students uh your uh
your viewers so someone on behalf of all
of them i needed to ask how do you
retain so much information do you revise
the things you read or uh
or do you just have a blessed memory sir
i wanted to know
i i don't know what it is i don't think
i'm exceptional or different from others
i just i'm i've always been curious
if you see if you are forced to read a
book and memorize things your brain will
rebel against that you will it will
ensure that you don't remember anything
but if you are genuinely interested in
something if you're watching a movie you
remember everything right
if you're watching an interesting movie
or an interesting tv series you're gonna
remember all of it because you you find
it interesting similarly if you are
interested in history or science or
philosophy or whatever if it is a
genuine interest and curiosity i think
you're going to retain that information
so that's how it's been for me i've been
reading since i was a little i was a
small kid whatever i could read i was
always curious
and maybe that's why i'm able to
remember things maybe that's the reason
i i've not done a psychoanalysis or
anything but possibly this you don't
revise anything you have read you just
you know keep on reading
no i i i forget lots of things i don't
remember everything i read
i forget whatever i find uninteresting
i read a lot and i think
most likely half of it i must be
forgetting whatever i don't find
interesting i don't i don't remember it
i don't finish every book cover to cover
i only read whatever i find interesting
that is a strategy that works for me
so you should actively forget things
which you don't find interesting maybe
that's how it works i don't know what it
is
thank you so much sir thank you thank
you so much for the question very nice
nice meeting you bye
all right all right who all do we have
let me bring in mr atharva
hello
[Music]
at least
foreign
jessica
right he was a king in northern india
shri krishna
he was a living breathing man who was
one of the greatest personalities
and one of the most impactful
personalities in human history
as as
he's the one who was never born and he's
the one who has never died he transcends
the universe
at some point in time
incarnations of divinity etcetera right
now
[Music]
this is a part of history we know the
turkic invasions of india
because of that we have the abrahamic
religions in india that's
how middle east
i respect that sir madam
is possible
it may be possible like it is not
incontrovertible evidence so from a
scientific perspective you have to
follow incontrovertible evidence only so
i would i have personally not seen
something that convinces me 100 percent
middle east
it has not been able to convince me one
hundred percent i would be very happy if
it was there but i have not found such
evidence
[Music]
foreign
very very very interesting suggestion
very good solution i will certainly take
it up okay
thank you so much very nice meeting you
thank you bye-bye
all right that was nice that was fun let
me take on somebody else who do we have
here we have goriji
hello
namaste
uh sir
uh thank you for picking me i had a
question
regarding
the democratic system that we follow in
india versus i mean in everywhere
wherever there is democracy
is it bias towards monotheistic
religions because in the west
the state religion i mean they don't
proclaim it but it's christian
whereas in india because we have this
hindu christian i mean abrahamic
religion mix so it favors more
i mean we see the voting pattern that
monastic a monotheistic religions what
and how they what versus how hindus what
so that's what my question is that is
there an inherent bias towards making
everything
monotheistic
right so
i think democracy itself by definition
can be implemented in whatever way you
want you can have a constitution that is
completely dharmic and laws that are
based in dharma and then you can have
democracy based on that
so democracy is just a system that you
can implement in whichever way you want
you can have an abrahamic uh
constitution abrahamic laws you can
declare your favorite abrahamic religion
as the state religion and you can have a
democracy based on that also
so the democracy the so-called democracy
that we have in india
it is
deeply flawed because the constitution
of india is a foreign constitution there
is nothing indian in it
it is not based on indian values it is
not based on indian
uh
principles it is not based on indian
traditions or culture it is based on
western ideas western concepts it's
completely western
the laws that are
uh enforced in india
they are also based on british laws
most of the laws are still remnants from
the british times
the institutions in india are
institutions the british created nothing
has changed after so-called independence
and that is why
india's entire system is so hindu phobic
it is it has turned into india into a
hindu phobic apartheid state in which
hindus are second-class citizens so i
don't think it's the
fault of democracy per se it is the four
it is the
the reason why india is so messed up is
because we never decolonized
after independence you're supposed to
throw out all the colonial baggage all
the colonial laws institutions all the
colonial people who have been serving
the british masters they need to be
thrown out
and an indian constitution should have
been put in place
indian officials who were pro-india and
not pro-british should have been
appointed and so on so forth the
education system should have been
decolonized everything this these things
never happened so it's as if
we are still ruled by the british by
proxy our our indians are ruling us on
behalf of the british that's how it's
become so that's the real problem it's
not the fault of democracy we had
democracy thousands of years ago during
shri krishna's time we had a certain
form of democracy which was an indian
form of democracy india is the mother of
democracy like our prime minister said a
few days ago
so it's not the fall of democracy it's
the fault of
the people to whom the power was given
by the british in 1947
okay
thank you
thank you for the question thank you
bye
all right let me bring in somebody else
somebody else
um
i'll take one more question for today
so whom should i bring let me bring in
mr deepak
hello sir
hello
uh handsome mumbai
okay
the question is uh
i came across a book recently uh
it was uh written
by uh father of allah
and the book came
around a century ago in early early
1920s
and the book claims that you know
the
the temples we have in india right like
you said we have i mean culture we had
in india and thousand years
we didn't have schools but uh students
used to learn in temples right that is
how we
used to go in india but uh what
he is claiming that
impulse uh you know and nowadays what we
see is uh um brahman's worshipping and
in
right
so what he's claiming that uh
that it is one it wasn't used to like
that so uh in era i mean in the century
of like 8th or 7th or 8th century
shankaracharya and his followers
tried to you know to cover all the
temples and he asked his followers to
you know uh
take charge of the temples and uh
universities like nalanda and
because uh what is claiming also that
in all those universities and these
temples like um
they had a buddhist
people were used to you know they used
to teach
in all those institutions
now brahmins were not there and he says
that uh
shinkana character
and
that is how the brahmins took over the
temples so what is your take on that
so i am not familiar with this book
i
haven't read it uh from what i
understand there was no killing of
anybody and uh
brahmins were not warriors they were not
killers
so uh
this seems to be inconsistent with the
fact that we have today if the book was
written 100 years ago clearly there was
some different uh world view at the time
that was prevalent
like i said mr uh
mr bal ganga darth was a firm believer
in the rn invasion theory right
about
120 years ago or so
so it is not the the fault of mr tilak
that he believed in it because at that
time
that was the widely accepted uh
wisdom that the irena that are invasion
of india of
aryan invasion of india actually
happened
so a hundred years ago 150 years ago
there was a completely different
perspective
and all the information that we have
today
was not available at that time today we
have science we have the internet we
have more discoveries and all all these
things that's why we know things
in a very different manner from what our
ancestors knew 100 years ago
so i don't know what exactly this
book says but if it says things like
that or things that are inconsistent
with the facts that we know today
it could possibly be because at that
time when the book was written those
facts may not have been available
or the prevailing consensus at that time
may have been what is written in the
book
so that's what i can say about it
because i have not actually studied the
book so i cannot give specific details
about that but it's you know times
change
and people's worldview changes based on
what uh information is available at that
point in time 150 years ago there was no
internet
there was no magazines there was no
libraries nothing they were under
british occupation so we had a different
understanding
and a different opinion of what our
history was today we know better today
we know something different but
that's the thing that the past is like a
foreign country things were very
different at the time
so that's what i can say sir
all right thank you so much thank you
nice meeting you
yeah same yeah good night
good night
all right uh ladies and gentlemen i
think i'm gonna have to end this year i
apologize to all of you who are waiting
in the queue but i'm gonna have to end
it here
so uh thank you so much for all your
questions for your participation it was
lovely talking to all of you and i will
keep doing this it's gonna be
great fun talking to all of you in
future episodes
thank you so much
thank you to all the viewers
and i will see you
in the next episode take care good night
bye